### JAGADISH PRASAD PRAJAPATI

#### FINANCIAL CONTROLLER



KANAN VIHAR, PL NO-106, PO- PATIA, BHUBANESWAR, ORISSA, INDIA

#### **PERSONAL INFO**

12thJune 1976
Nationality: Indian
Gender: Male
Religion: Hindu
Marital Status: Married

#### **CONTACT**

Mobile No. +91 7978340476 Mobile No. +917325955107 Whtup no.+974 33538661

Passport No. U5446186

Prajapatij952@gmail.com jagadish\_jp160@yahoo.com

Skype: jagdish72

#### **LANGUAGES**

English, Dhivehi, Arabic, Hindi, Odia, Nepali, Marathi

#### **OBJECTIVE**

Responsible for ensuring that all accounting allocations are appropriately made and documented. Managing and leading the finance operations, support the business as Financial Controller and help the hotel management and owning company to achieve its financial and overall objectives.

#### SUMMARY

Experienced finance professional with proven track record in the hospitality sector over 13 years, including 3 years in leadership roles, I started my career with a strong focus on finance.

MBA in Finance

I have a strong operational background, especially in planning, preopening and cost containment.

#### **MAIN DUTIES & RESPONSIBILITIES**

- ✓ Oversee all company accounts and investments.
- ✓ Create monthly and annual reports to identify results, trends, and financial forecasts.
- Manage cash flow by tracking transactions and regularly reviewing internal reports.
- ✓ Supervise and manage financial department staff, including accountants and finance team members.
- Motivate and lead finance team members by clarifying roles and providing helpful.
- ✓ Suggest updates and improvements for accounting systems, including payroll and invoicing.
- Ensure that all financial transactions are properly recorded, filed, and reported.
- ✓ Establish and implement financial reporting systems to comply with government regulations and legislation.
- ✓ Collaborate with auditing services to ensure proper compliance with all regulations.
- ✓ Develop budgets and financial plans for the company based on research and data reports.
- ✓ Review all financial plans and budgets regularly to look for cost reduction opportunities
- ✓ Examine all financial reports and data closely to check for discrepancies.
- ✓ Create systems to prevent errors in data collection and calculations.
- ✓ Report to the CFO with timely and accurate financial information.

#### **EDUCATION**

Master of Business Administration (2012) Faculty of Commerce Karnataka University

Bachelor's Degree in Commerce (B.Com) 1997 Faculty of Commerce Utkal University

Intermediate in Commerce (I.Com) 1994 Faculty of Commerce Council of Higher Secondary Education

#### **TRAINING**

- Leadership.
- · Seven Habits.
- Guest Courtesy Techniques.
- Loyalty.
- Finance for Non Finance.
- Essential Skills Training Program for staff.
- First Aid Tanning.

#### **PERSONAL SKILLS**

- Process excellent communication skills.
- Planning time Management.
- Problem Solving skills
- Team Work.
- Reliable & Dependable.
- Decision Making Skills.
- Strategic Thinking.
- Job Knowledge.

### **WORK HISTORY**

**Financial Controller –** TIME Hotels, TIME Rako Hotel Doha from January 2018 to till date.

- Formulating innovative business strategies and assisting the company in annual budgeting and forecasting; effectively redesign budgets for all capital & operational requirements. Maximizing budgetary control to achieve desired financial performance.
- Formulating innovative business strategies and assisting the company in annual budgeting and forecasting; effectively redesign budgets for all capital & operational requirements. Maximizing budgetary control to achieve desired financial performance.
- ✓ Conceptualized and implemented accounting policies/ principles and tracking systems for various functional areas; ensured compliance with accounting standards & procedures and finalization of various accounts within time bound schedules.
- ✓ Dispense all month end financial data in accordance with International Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS).
- ✓ Monitoring expenses & profit performance and suggesting corrective action, reviewing Standard Operating Procedures, Internal Audit Findings & other operational issues, contracts and license.
- ✓ Generate and ensure management companies best practices and SOPs to enhance revenue, guest service and productivity.
- ✓ Utilizing interpersonal and excellent communication skills to lead, influence, and encourage others; advocates sound financial/business decision making; demonstrated honesty/integrity; leads by example.
- ✓ Spearheaded all statutory compliance, finance and accounting policies and procedures of the hotel.
- ✓ Engage, train, counsel, supervise, coach and evaluate performance of the staffing of fifteen.

**Finance Manager**- Epicurean Hotels & Lifestyle Thailand from November 2015 to Dec 2017.

- ✓ Guided finance functions involving designing & implementing systems, policies & procedures to facilitate internal financial controls towards the accomplishment of organizational goals.
- ✓ Effectively advised the management on operational expenditure/control and strategically plan & implement innovative restructuring strategies on various financial and statutory aspects.
- ✓ Skill fully conducted regular reviews & analysis and shared performance data with the management for achievement of the desired financial results.
- ✓ Launched fund management of the property; reviewed the profitability of business to assess the accuracy of revenue and expenditure accounted. Also, developed systems and procedures that achieve higher cost efficiency.
- ✓ Executed on going analytical support by monitoring the operating department's actual and projected sales, expenditure and profit margin.
- ✓ Analyzed information, forecasts sales against expenses and created appropriate annual budget plans.
- ✓ Performed close watch on Revenue Management functions. Officiated entire hotel operations in the absence of Dir of finance.
- ✓ Ensured a strong financial and operational control environment to safeguard assets, improve operations, business value and profitability.
- ✓ Provided excellent business leadership by assigning clear accountability to team members and other departments' managers.

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

- Back office system (Boss, Navision, Sun 6.0, Vision Excel, Bayan, Jana)
- Front Office (Opera, Fidelio, Prolific)
- Inventory System (FMC, MC, Prolific)
- HR Payroll- Prolific
- F& B Micros

#### **MY OBJECTIVES**

 To achieve challenging and professional environment in the field of accounting, which also encompasses purchases and stores departments. This will enhance my skills and knowledge and along with the organizational development gain personal development and brighten career prospectus.

## APPRECIATION & PERSONAL ACHIEVEMENT

- Best Employee Award winner in 2007 in Jan., May & August (Hideaway Spa Resorts & Marina)
- Best Employee Award winner-2012 (Amari Doha)

## **Assistant Finance Manager -** Jumeirah Group / Jumeirah Hotels & Resorts from August 2014 to October 2015.

- Review & Approval of General journal voucher.
- ✓ Profit & Loss variance analysis
- ✓ Bank reconciliation statement review and approval.
- ✓ Inter unit debit & credit note review and approval.
- Prepayments & Accrued expenses schedule preparation and review
- ✓ Accounts receivable and payable Supervision.
- ✓ Performance report preparation and distribution to higher management.
- ✓ Preparing weekly flash reports, including Food cost/ General store issue summary/ Fuel consumption cost/ Staff canteen cost/ Fuel cost per guest room.
- ✓ Month end system closing & month end reports (Food/ Beverage/ Tobacco/ Fuel cost/ General store issue cost).
- ✓ Controlling of food cost through monitoring market list and by maintaining minimum and maximum.

# **Accounts Supervisor-** Amari Hotel Doha (Owned by Onyx Hospitality Group Thailand) From July 2012 July to 2014 July.

- ✓ Verifies the Sales report, room variance report, daily cheque/cash register and general cashier report.
- ✓ Payment to Vender & verifies Venders aging report.
- ✓ Is responsible for maintaining the General Ledger.
- ✓ Ensures all house banks are counted on a monthly basis.
- ✓ Reconciles all related party payments.
- ✓ Review monthly checklists.
- ✓ Responsible for Accounts department in the absence of FM.
- ✓ Prepare daily/weekly/monthly/annual income & statistics reports required for the senior Management as well as for the Owning Company.
- ✓ Inter-companies Accounts reconciliation
- ✓ Conduct various audits to ensure that the revenue generated is captured in the system.
- ✓ Check and reconcile General Cashier's report and ensure Deposit match with collection
- ✓ Conduct spot checks of cash counts of all house bank holders.
- ✓ Effectively communicate with other department and section heads, with the aim of ensuring resort income is controlled properly and allocate them their respective revenue accounts.
- ✓ Review accounts payable monthly inventory reconciliations
- ✓ Prepares all journal vouchers for month-end closing

#### **MY STRENGTHS**

- Financial Management/ Financial Accounting / Management Accounting/Reporting.
- Cost Management / Variance Analysis / System Control
- Suppliers Management / Planning of product orders / Inventory Management
- Debtors Management / Presenting debtors at the **Management Meetings**
- Product Costing / Pre-Costing / Pricing / **Discount Approvals**
- Expertise in computerized accounting systems from the journal to final accounts in the international standards and formats.

#### **MY WEAKNESSES**

- Demanding with a constant drive to succeed.
- Tend to become dominating and autocratic when strict deadlines need to be met I tend to lead most of the times. rather than being a follower work addict

**Accountant** -Addu Amari Resort, Maldives (Owned by Onyx Hospitality Group Thailand Pre-Opening), From June 2011 to June 2012.

- ✓ Preparation of bank reconciliation statement
- ✓ Analyzing of Income.✓ Analyzing of Expenses
- ✓ Preparation and posting monthly journals✓ Preparation of MIS Report
- ✓ Preparation of production report
- ✓ Ensuring that the GST, and Green Tax and other statutory payments are made and the returns are filed on time.
- ✓ Revenue Journal posting.
- ✓ Prepares Daily Report for Finance Manager.
- ✓ Audits Night Auditor's Reports and F&B Revenue Reports seeing to it that all transactions are properly supported and reconciled.
- ✓ Audits the General Cashier's Report and computes averages/shortages of cashiers
- ✓ Checks deposit slips against total collections per General Cashier's report.
- ✓ Conducts physical count of all house funds at least once a week.

**Senior Assistant-Accountant -**The Island Hideaway Spa Resorts & Marina at Dhonakulhi Maldives (Owned and Operated by Lily Hotel Pte Ltd) from Oct 2006 to April 2011.

- ✓ Purchase Journal posting.
- ✓ Payment to Supplier.
- ✓ Cash Flow (Monthly supplier payment forecast).
- ✓ Monthly analysis of Store consumption report.
- ✓ Reconciliation of Cash- Weekly & monthly.
- ✓ Reconciliation of Inventory monthly.
- ✓ Booking of expenses invoice.
- Monitoring and Implementing Standards Operation Procedures with Regard to the Operation.
- ✓ Preparation of Financial statement (MIS)
- Interacting actively with the statutory and internal auditors of the company for audit and finalization.
- ✓ Monitoring & Supervising F&B Functions, AR Functions, AP Functions & Night Audit Function.
- ✓ Preparing Revenue Forecasts.
- ✓ Handling External Audits.
- ✓ Preparing GTS & Bed Tax report.
- ✓ Liaison with Banks and fund management.

#### **OPPORTUNITIES**

Experience of 2 pre-opening Resorts.

Wide International experience of working in place like (Onyx, Epicuren,)

Work experience within international Chains Like Onyx Hospitality, Jumeirah Group, Time Hospitality & Epicurean Hotels & Lifestyle

Experience of directly working under DOF & CFO and Financial Controller.

#### **INTERESTS**

Reading Newspaper, Book, Swimming, Playing Cricket, Yoga, Nature Photography.

#### **REFERENCES**

References and Certificate document available on request.

Night Auditor - The Old Anchor, (Dalmia Resort) Goa, India from Jan 2003 to Feb 2005.

- ✓ Checking guest registration card everyday basic.
- ✓ Checking F&B Mini Bar, Banquet sales
- ✓ Debtor's serialization and authorization.
- ✓ Various vouchers issued on the day.
- ✓ Arrival / Departure for the day report.
- ✓ Daly Basic Checking Govt. Tax report form Opera.

- ✓ Daily Basic Checking Govt. Tax report form Opera.
   ✓ Allowance vouchers check with authorization.
   ✓ Guests In-house report checking.
   ✓ Room Plan/Sale/Verification Report checking.
   ✓ Ensures all revenue transactions recorded and consistent and carried out according to our standard procedures.

**Audit Assistant —**Price water house Coopers Maldives (PWC) Audit Assistant from Dec 1999 to Dec 2002.

Audit Assistant (Part Qualified Chartered Accountant) -P K Sahoo Co. & Associate- Charted Accountancy Firm -Bhubaneswar, Orissa, India from Jan 1999 to Nov 1999.